<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new suruey of the affaires of Europe With other remarkable accidents, not yet published by the ordinary posts, but faithfully collected out of letters of credit and good relations.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.96</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849823</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14994</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14994)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 788:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new suruey of the affaires of Europe With other remarkable accidents, not yet published by the ordinary posts, but faithfully collected out of letters of credit and good relations.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Eld?] for Nathaniel Butter, Bartholomew Downes, and Thomas Archer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Now = Newsbooks 96.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 10569.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10569 on UMI microfilm reel 788.</note>
                  <note>Pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14994:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW SVRVEY OF THE AFFAIRES <hi>of</hi> EVROPE.</p>
            <p>WITH <hi>Other remarkable accidents, not yet</hi> publiſhed by the ordinary Poſts, but <hi>faithfully collected out of Letters of credit and good Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter, Bartholomew Downes,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14994:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14994:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Conſtantinople.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas you haue a long time expected ſome relation of newes, and diſcourſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the affaires of Europe; alas, you muſt conſider what you doe, when you come into a well furniſhed Garden, you ſee the froſt and the ſnow hath nipped the flowers, and there is ſcarce any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance either of ſweet herbes or flouriſhing plants: only the roots remaine ſafe in the ground, and peraduenture at the ſpring through the warmth of the Sunne, and the nature of the ſoile aſſume as it were new life, and ſhew forth ſome beautifull hanſomneſſe, ſo hath the winter delt with the affaires of Europe, the Souldiers haue beene glad of refreſhing, and the Princes taken care to make them ſtrong with eaſe and quietneſſe, but now the Spring comming for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the ſtorme of cold ouer-blowne, you ſhall ſee peraduenture the roots to receiue a ſtrange freſhneſſe, and new buſineſſe, ſhew you a face both of terrour and pleaſure: till when I will be bold to vnſeale certaine Letters which ſhall tell you of certaine well manured grounds, which euen this winter haue brought forth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14994:3"/>ſome flowers, and ſimple although they proue <hi>Antipathies</hi> in nature to ſome conſtitutions: the Letters then from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> aſſure vs thus much, that whereas <hi>Daout Baſhaw,</hi> the ſetter vp of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> after the ſtrangling of <hi>Oſman,</hi> who had married one of the daughters of the Empreſſe, proiected not onely the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Empire, but the ouerruling of the Emperour: yea peraduenture the aduancing of his poſterity to the throne of <hi>Othoman,</hi> by foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in a ſonne of his own, and then to ſtrangle the yong brothers of <hi>Oſman,</hi> and ſo to follow with the death of <hi>Muſtapha.</hi> The new Viceer, called <hi>Huzein Baſhaw,</hi> comming from <hi>Gran Cairo,</hi> as a giuer of Antidotes to the poiſon of theſe turmoiles, had no better meanes to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the frame of his greatneſſe, then to call <hi>Daout Baſhaw</hi> &amp; the Empreſſe in queſtion for ſo perfidious a plot, and dangerous a treaſon: The woman either transformed her ſelfe, and ſo was obſcured: or corrupted the Officers of State, &amp; ſo was remitted; or confeſſed all to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Mufty, and ſo was pardoned. But the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw, the Ianiſaries not enduring his Apology, was preſently cut in pieces: ſo that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> after many changes is now in the hands of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zein Baſhaw,</hi> who taking example by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer affrightings, hideth as yet his panther ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ients of policy concerning the augmentation of his owne honour, and falleth directly to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14994:3"/>ſetting vpright the ſtaggering Common-wealth, and adding as it were a tincture to the beauty of the Othoman glory, wherein he hath proceeded in ſuch a manner, and with ſo rare a diſcipline, that when hee ſacrificed as it were 200. Ianiſaries, who had beene delinquents in the murther to the ghoſt of <hi>Oſman,</hi> all the reſt endured the puniſhment and gaue a plaudit to his loyalty. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> in the meane time ſits like a ſhadow, and is glad of the peace which <hi>Huzein Baſhaws</hi> gouernment hath eſtabliſhed, louing him becauſe he hath effected the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the Souldiers toward him, and fearing himſelfe becauſe he hath already ſeene what the malignity of time hath done, and the inſolent Souldier is ready to put in practice.</p>
               <p>For euen the other day when the people were diſtaſted with <hi>Muſtaphus</hi> puſillanimity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the heroicke ſprightfulneſſe of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered <hi>Oſman,</hi> when they heard of the tumults of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and the ſuſpicious reuolts of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawes of <hi>Aleppo</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> when ſome had whiſpered in their eares, O what a difference is there betweene the magnanimous countenance and maieſticall preſence of <hi>Oſman,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected aſpect of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who men would iudge to be fitter for a Monaſtry then a Palace; or to pray in a Cel rather then rule in a Throne: they ſuddenly called for the ſight of <hi>Oſmans</hi> brethren, who very politikely without any delay
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14994:4"/>
                  <hi>Huzein Baſhaw</hi> brought out of the <hi>Serali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and aduanced in the <hi>Hippodrame,</hi> aſſuring the ſouldiers, that neither it was <hi>Muſtaphaes</hi> pleaſure, nor any motiues of Superiours, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to obſcure them or diſappoint them: onely there was reaſon by no meanes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locate <hi>Muſtapha</hi> now raigning, conſidering their young yeeres, and the ſuſpitious trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the confining Princes. For if any new tumults ſhould ariſe out of the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of diſorder, God knowes what the Perſian might doe in Aſia and Arabia, and the Emperour and King of Poland in Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary and <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> conſidering they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready thriued againſt their enemies on euery ſide: therefore he commanded them to qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe and ſilence, and demand of him an account of the Princes, when occaſion ſhould ſerue. In this manner was his wiſdome ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that the flames of this new ſedition were delicately quenched: the Princes retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the pallace: <hi>Muſtapha</hi> eſtabliſhed in the Throne, himſelfe preuailed with their good opinion, and the whole body of the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> recouered from the growing infection of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolts and diſorder, ſo that the city was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly quieted, and all good gouernement obſerued.</p>
               <p>Much about this time, which was in Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber laſt, ſome will haue the <hi>Perſian</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14994:4"/>to ariue; as well to gratefie the new enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> as to renew the old and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary treaties of peace: ſome againe ſay there was no new Embaſſador, but that the Ligier there, had ſeuerall directions from <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> both to preſent the Emperor certaine gifts, and to gratefie the <hi>Viceer</hi> for his indulgent care ouer the Common-wealth, in ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſuſpitious times of innouation. And alſo to aſſociate himſelfe with the Engliſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, and preſent him with a Target of gold, and other gifts in behalfe of the <hi>Sophy</hi> his Lord, and by reaſon of the ſeruices, the Engliſh had done him at <hi>Ormus,</hi> who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon tooke a conuenient time, and by way of Viſitation came vnto him, vſing theſe or the like ſpeeches.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p> I am commiſſioned from my great Maſter,
<note place="margin">The Perſian Ambaſſador to the Engliſh Ambaſſador.</note> the <hi>Sophy</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> not onely to viſit you, but gratefie you with ſuch preſents as befitteth him to beſtow, and you to receiue: the motiues ariſing from the high deſeruings of your nation, and the noble renoune of your Prince: For if Marchants or if you pleaſe Marchants Factors, can merit ſo well of fame, as to equall great Commanders in heroick acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what doe the Nobles and Gentiles deſerue, who queſtionleſſe giue good example to the reſt, and cannot but reioyce the kings heart to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14994:5"/>haue ſuch ſubiects, and worthy ſouldiers: but to the purpoſe. The trafficke of ſilke being long ſince ſetled at <hi>Ormus,</hi> the Portingalls poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing certaine places about <hi>Iaſques,</hi> on the Eaſterne ſide of the Perſian Gulph, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged by the great <hi>Mogull</hi> of the hither <hi>India,</hi> not only debarred all commers as men ſay, but by extraordinary meanes, and force ſurpriſed the Caſtle, and Iland of <hi>Ormus:</hi> which when my great Lord vnderſtood after mature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideration, as vnwilling to endure the indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, beſides the loſſe of his prerogatiues and cuſtomes, hee capitulated with the Engliſh, and vpon certaine conditions by way of ſalary entertainement, admitted them to his ſeruice, and committed the managing of the affaires to their endeuours; ſo an army was prepared, but becauſe the Caſtle could not be obtained, nor the Iland cleered without great Ordnance, and that the Engliſh ſhips lay ſo conueniently in the Gulph, hee likewiſe hired their Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and after many skirmiſhes, time and their owne valour, mounted two hundred peeces, and banded three hundred men, who demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues ſo valiantly, and beſtowed their ſhot ſo effectually, that by degrees wee were Lords of the Iland, and abſolute Maſters of the towne; the <hi>Portingals</hi> not able to endure the encounters, nor braue aſſaults without loſſe and ſome ſlaughters.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14994:5"/>
               <p>Thus by degrees they won the Iland, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed the <hi>Portugals</hi> out of the Towne, nothing remaining but the fortified Caſtle, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained but a while; for the defendants foreſeeing an vtter deſtruction by holding out, conſidering our <hi>Perſians</hi> were euery where ſo malitious and violent againſt them, gained the ſauing of their liues by orderly compoſition, and ſo quite aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the place, and we were quickly maſters of all; which without flattery or other inſinuation, it pleaſeth my great Maſter to attribute to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and vnmatchable valour of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and for which he hath recompenced euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſeruing, and is contented that the trafficke for Silke ſhal remaine free to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and halfe the cuſtomes of the Towne and Iland of <hi>Ormus</hi> be as it were a yeerely compenſation to the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company at your City of <hi>London.</hi> And thus much for <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Poland.</head>
               <p>You haue often heard how the <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Coſſacks</hi> of <hi>Bogdonia</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> liue for the moſt part vpon ſpoile and robberies of Merchants, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the wars imploy them, or they imploy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the ſeruices of other Princes, which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome it ſeemes they ſtill retain: for euen the other day as bad men (though enemies) ſoone agree to commit outrages, &amp; any villanie to enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: ſo did they combine to forrage into <hi>Ruſsia,</hi> and went ſo farre, and preuailed ſo well, that if an embucy from <hi>Moſio</hi> had not acquainted King <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmond</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14994:6"/>with the miſchiefe and forcible attempts they had queſtionleſſe kindled a fire which a great deale of water could not haue quenched: but thus diſappointed at that time, and vnderſtanding of a truce and limited peace betweene the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and that alſo the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Germany,</hi> though there were great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for warre, was vnwilling to entertaine them, or to indure their vnrulineſſe either in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> or <hi>Bohemia,</hi> they went another way to worke, and concluded with the <hi>Tartars</hi> to lay a Plot vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the City of <hi>Leopolis,</hi> which being diſcouered by certaine poore Pedlars men and women of the ſame trade the Inhabitants preuented. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of their abode and places of aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they made a braue ſally, and by the aſſiſtance of the Villages, not onely diſſipated their meetings and diſappointed their pretended villany, but put diuers of them to the ſword, and by many fearfull ſlaughters compelled them out of thoſe Confines, ſo that they were enforced to hide themſelues in the woods, and flie to the borders of the blacke Sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Tranſiluania.</head>
               <p>AS after great windes and fearefull tempeſts, though the ayre is calme, and they ſeeme ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, the Sea yet remaines turbulent, and the billowes mount a great while: ſo fared it with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14994:6"/>buſineſſe and affayres of <hi>Turky,</hi> though the Citie was quieted, and the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> ſeemed appeaſed, yet euery man was almoſt affrighted, and the whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering Troops amaſed the <hi>Baſhawes,</hi> as if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining Princes were vp in armes, not onely to take reuenge, as acting one anothers part on ſuch tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors as durſt lay hands vpon their Prince, and ſuch a Monarch; but to worke their owne ends for ſuch places, and recouery of ſuch Countries, as the <hi>Turkes</hi> had vſurped both in <hi>Perſia</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherupon the <hi>Vizier Hazein Baſshaw</hi> by way of preuention very cautelous demeaned himſelfe, and in the name of his Emperour <hi>Muſtapha</hi> ſent out his ſeuerall Ambaſſadors for the renouation of thoſe ancient contracts &amp; conditions of peace betweene the Princes of Aſia and Europe, and yet retayning the maieſty of the <hi>Othoman</hi> glory, hee inſinuated with none, but the <hi>Perſian,</hi> and <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Germany:</hi> onely hee laid a ſtrict command vpon the <hi>Baſshawes</hi> of the Prouinces, both to maintaine the dignity of the Common-wealth, and the peace of the Cities.</p>
               <p>Among whom the Ambaſſador that came to the Emperour, not onely obtayned a reſolute combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of peace, but a faire admiſſion of amitie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the <hi>Tranſiluanian Prince</hi> had a relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of his tribute, and augmentation of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, ſo that hee thought it meet to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with the Emperour, that he might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preuent the incurſions and abuſes of the <hi>Iani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries,</hi> if they ſhould in this turbulent time either
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14994:7"/>breake into <hi>Hungary,</hi> or trouble his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: but the <hi>Baſſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> being as carefull as himſelfe, had alwayes preparations ready, both to intercept the malignity of time, concerning his own rebels, and the terror of trouble from the <hi>Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks</hi> of <hi>Poland:</hi> in all which he was countenanced by the Emperor, and emboldned through this new combination of peace betweene the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the great <hi>Turke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Vienna.</head>
               <p>THe Emperor as it were thriuing in all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, in the acquiſition of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the preuailings of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> eſpecially in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing of a ſeditious tumult in <hi>Prague,</hi> where he ſhewed them the power of a ſtronger arme, and taught them this diſcipline, that the end of treaſon was death, and puniſhment attended the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents againſt the law; ſeemed yet weary of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and practiſed another way, yea diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies (as I may ſay) to corroborate his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and reconcile the affaires of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. Firſt, he proclaimed peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erneſſe to all that would returne to his obedience. Secondly, he admitted the Prince of <hi>Anholt</hi> and many Lords into his fauour; yea he repealed the proſcriptions of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iaggendorf,</hi> the Counts of <hi>Thorne</hi> father and ſonne, and others who had maintained <hi>Glatz,</hi> and the reuolted Townes of <hi>Morauia</hi> againſt him; who yet ſtood on their guard, and kept themſelues ſecure in their faſt holds. Thirdly, hee countenanced the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14994:7"/>in <hi>Vienna</hi> and many other places, whereby they continued their aſſemblies, ſo that you ſhall haue 50. Coaches at a Sermon: and in <hi>Stiria, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia, Corrinola, Croatia,</hi> they meet without feare or danger, yea they pray for their brethren in the <hi>Valtoline:</hi> all which he endures, and ſees a great alteration by this quiet courſe and conniuency. Fourthly, he hath changed many gouernors both in <hi>Morauia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and written to the Biſhops to be as ſparing in their authortty, as may ſtand with the dignity of the <hi>Romane Church.</hi> Fiftly, hee hath proclaimed diuers Diets and Aſſemblies at <hi>Auſpurg, Regenſpurg, Ratisbona,</hi> and other places, whither he hath gone with his Empreſſe in perſon, and beene entertained with triumphs, inuiting as it were the Princes of the Empire to maintaine their accuſtomed ſolemnities, and decide the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent controuerſies for the rectifying the diſorders of the Common-wealth. Laſt of all, perceiuing a kind of thinneſſe in theſe Aſſemblies, and that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saxony, Brandenburg, Brunſwicke, Heſs,</hi> nor many other Princes graced the places with their preſence; he cauſed the Empreſſe to write vnto the Duke of <hi>Saxony;</hi> whoſe Letters were to this effect:</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>My Lord:</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <note place="margin">The Empreſſe Letter to the Duke of Saxony.</note>
                     <p>I will neither meddle with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors affaires, nor your diſcontents; nay I would not haue ſo much liberty giuen to a woman, for feare of irregularity, eſpecially in tranſcendent bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and aboue the ſhort reaches of her ſex. l will onely challenge my owne rights, and take vpon me to defend the honour and prerogatiue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14994:8"/>which belongs to my place: I had thought then that for my ſake you would haue come to the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et at <hi>Regenſpurg,</hi> and out of noble reſpects either welcomed me into the Country, or giuen good example to others by your obſeruation. When I was in my Fathers houſe, I haue heard <hi>Gonzala</hi> boaſt of <hi>Saxonies</hi> loue, and although we had ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter to talke of your greatneſſe, yet wee left all to thinke of your honor and affinity to the Emperor. How comes then this ſlackneſſe to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit me that am <hi>Gonzalaes</hi> ſiſter, and <hi>Ferdinandos</hi> wife? Is it becauſe you are offended or diſtaſted with the affaires? Come a Gods name, and leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate theſe tumors; ſhew your griefes, and iuſtifie your Apology, and by the faith of a Princeſſe, whoſe innocency warrants your ſafe conduct, I will not leaue kneeling before his Imperiall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; nay our Ladies Altar, vntill a perfect recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation be made, and your Honor acknowledged to be a great ſupportation of the Empire.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Valtoline.</head>
               <p>It hath beene heretofore generally proclaimed that whoſoeuer would obey the Church of Rome, and ſubmit to the Spaniſh gouernment, ſhould haue reſtauration of eſtates, and quietneſſe of life; but many conteſted againſt it, and the preuailers turned their admonitions into fury, and ran ouer the Country with ſlaughter: ſome they beheaded &amp; ſet vpon poles; ſome they cut out their tongues, ſome they puniſhed in other manner, and ſome they ſent into the inquiſition at <hi>Millane;</hi> amongſt whom as the Souldiers in their ſearches lighted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14994:8"/>vpon certaine Miniſters, and Noblemen and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, there was a Gentlewoman of great yeares in the rancke of our Ladies, foureſcore at the leaſt, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Maddona Paola,</hi> who was at the firſt intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many perſwaſiue reaſons to forſake her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and come to the vnity of the Mother Church: but her reply was the Story of the three Children, who would not kneele to <hi>Nabuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> Image, and when they added the terror of the puniſhment, ſhee ſmiled in their faces and told them they ſhould ſee the Angell to protect her, which anſwer they imputed to frenzie and the dotage of her yeares, and ſo all enrag'd and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated, they reuiled her and condemned her to the fire, yea to bee burnt in a publike <hi>Piazza:</hi> ſo the inquiſitors went cautelouſly to worke, and not only bound her hands but gagd her mouth, and ſo brought her to the ſtake among them all: but it ſhould ſeeme the fire had quickly power of her cordes and her hands were as quickly at liberty, ſo that ere ſhee dyed ſhee ſhewed ſuch ſignes of ioy &amp; alacrity of ſpirit, ſuch a liuely countenance, ſuch clapping of her hands, ſuch lifting them vp to heauen, ſuch pointing to the people, and then to heauen, that ere ſhe was confumed to cynders, the thouſands of people ſhed as many teares, and departed a way murmurring and diſcontented. In this eſtate ſtandeth the whole Country of the <hi>Grizons</hi> at this hower, and ſo by the aduice of the <hi>Swiffe,</hi> they haue implored the Maieſty of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Signory</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the States of the vnited
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14994:9"/>Prouinces, to ſpeak cheerful things to their ſoules, and not to ſee them ſubiect to the authority of ſtrangers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Naples.</head>
               <p>AFter the arriuall of the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> as Viceroy, and that the Seas were filled with Gallies and Turkiſh <hi>Carmiſans,</hi> which <hi>Hazein Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> had ſent abroad to watch the proceedings of <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> in this time of turbulency on all ſides: the gouernment was ſo ſearcht and looked into, and yet with that affability and inſinuating care, that the mutinies and ſeditions formerly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, were now appeaſed, the famine preuented, the Merchant welcomed, diuers Noblemen diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged out of priſon, the factions reconciled, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny debts payed, the money enhawnſed, and a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reformation followed, which once eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, then beganne a muſter in <hi>Calabria, Brutia, Apuleia,</hi> yea <hi>Cicilia</hi> it ſelfe, and at laſt certaine troopes of horſe and Companies liſted for any new emploiment, as the directions of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould giue them notice: but as yet they heare of no filuer Fleet arriued: ſo that in truth, though ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour haue beene too lauiſh in ouer-numbring the Souldiers: yet there is a great probability, that there ſhall an army be raiſed in <hi>Italy</hi> to attend the Duke of <hi>Feria</hi> in his proiects at <hi>Millane,</hi> where at this houre there is a great ſuſpition of reuolting, as you ſhall heare in due place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14994:9"/>
               <head>From Rome.</head>
               <p>They write from hence, that there was neuer ſo Wiſe, Honourable, and iudicious a Counſell about the Pope, as is now, nor were there Cardinals in their Conclaue ſo repoſed, and addicted to reformation before: Inſomuch that many enormities haue beene puniſhed, and both Prieſts, Fryers, and Curtezans, reſtrained from that former iuſtifying of their impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous liues in ſo publicke a manner, yea many good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees haue of late beene enacted, and ſundry Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions ſent abroad to be practiſed.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt, that there was a new Bull proclaymed, for auoyding all deceit and partiality in Electing their Popes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, that thoſe wonderfull fulminations againſt Heretickes, ſhould not be executed with Fire and Sword in ſo publique a manner as was wont: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that whereas the moſt expected the Biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> ſhould haue beene condemned to the Fire, hee was pardoned, reconciled, and admitted to enioy his honours and ſubſtance.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, Cardinall <hi>Burgheſius</hi> falling out with a Ieſuite, called him buſie body, and tolde him to his face, that if euer the Church ſuffered Diminution and decay of glory, it might thanke the Ieſuites, who had beene the cauſe of all the combuſtions of Europe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly, that although the rotten branches of the Vine were to be broken, pruned, and cut off, yea caſt into the Fire, which is meant by obſtinate Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes: yet was it no Doctrine of the mother Church
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14994:10"/>to deſtroy innocent ſoules with the refractary wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, nor ſlaughter ignorant Nouices before admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory counſell, and aduiſe for their conuerſion.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, that the Cardinals ſhould maintaine their eminent Dignity and places, how euer men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt their originals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Venice.</head>
               <p>The affaires of the <hi>Grizons</hi> ouer-clouded with ſo many misfortunes, drawe them from the line of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the meanes of preſeruations, and ſo by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adiutement of the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> their neighbours, they not onely acquainted their confederates with the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that had plunged them into the gulph of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, but implored the aſſiſtance of many Princes to remember the <hi>Antiqua foedera,</hi> &amp; not ſuffer them to be forſaken in this loſſe of their Liberty, and troubling of their conſcience: amongſt whom it is ſaid, that one <hi>Andrea Planta</hi> was ſent to the Signiory of <hi>Venice</hi> with intimation of their Eſtates, and imploration of their helpe, who was ſo well entertained, that his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage was not onely accepted, but many faire promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes returned to their ſatisfaction: his Meſſage had theſe or the like paſſages.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="message">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Grizons meſſage to Venice.</head>
                     <p>HIgh and Mighty: I come not to renouate your memoryes, concerning the combination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs, and the amitv of our Countries, nor to meddle with the cauſe of Religion, which of it ſelfe were ſufficient to moue a pitty: but to plead the policies of State, and vrge an ancient poſition by way of Caution: <hi>Tum tuares agitur, paries cumproximus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det,</hi> your Marchants cannot Traficke into Germany, and vent the commodities of your Countrey, for now
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14994:10"/>all is ſtopt, or blockt vp, ſo that you muſt with a vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant eye fore-ſee the danger to come and preuent the worſt: you ſee what is done already, neither could the Snow of the mountaines, nor the Mountaines themſelues, the paſſages of the Woods, the cut out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, the ſteepy aſcendings, the plaſhing of the pines, the anfractus of the Hilles, the roaring of the Waters, the danger of the pits hinder them, but they are come thus farre already: They began with the Fort <hi>Fuentes,</hi> they continued with their Garriſons in many places, and now they haue ended in a manner with the poſſeſſion of our whole Territories, ſo that if this inundation be not ſtopped, iudge your ſelues, whether it will flow, if it breake down the bankes, &amp; if we be not relieued in time, may it not proue a rub to gall others, aſwell as our ſelues: therefore I leaue it to your further conſideration, and ſo without either ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauating the cauſe, or exaſperating the aduerſary, I conclude, that there is no husbandry in letting theſe plants ouerſpread the ground.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>To this effect was the Meſſage of the Grizons, but their Anſwer was not publiſhed, onely it was whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if the King of <hi>France</hi> did not ſend the Duke <hi>de Rohan,</hi> as principall Commaunder, they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite Count <hi>Mansfeld</hi> to vndertake the buſines, and be Lieutenant Generall of thoſe Forces, which ſhould be there imployed: in the meane while they fortefied all the maritine Townes of <hi>Hiſtria,</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> filled the Gulph with Gallyes, and ſent two Galenzes to lye betweene the point of <hi>Calabria</hi> and <hi>Candy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Geneua.</head>
               <p>The great reſort of Noble men and women out of <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Grizons</hi> and <hi>France</hi> in the time of theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14994:11"/>troubles and perſecutions to <hi>Geneua,</hi> as a ſanctuary hath filled both the Towne ſo the Countrey, that a great dearth and famine followed, inſomuch that Wheat exceeded our rates, &amp; a Buſhel is worth twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings ſterling, whereupon the Magiſtrates fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome greater miſchiefe, as that the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> would take aduantage on their diſtreſſe and peſtring of people, becauſe they heard of diuers Muſtrings, and that the King of France determined to meet him at <hi>Lions:</hi> But God hath the keyes of the hearts of Princes, and openeth and ſhutteth them at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: ſo they heard no more of hoſtile inuaſion, nor a word was whiſpered of any proiects againſt them, not withſtanding they ſtood on their guard, and beſides their continuall Prayers within, had as continuall Garriſons and watches without, ſo that withall care and diligence they fortified their Ports, and manned their Fortifications: yea ſuch was the eſpeciall fauour of God towards them, that all other prouiſion bare low prices, and for all this ſcarcity of Corne, their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neighbours and aduerſaries, I meane the Catholike <hi>Cantons</hi> and <hi>Bazill</hi> it ſelfe, ſupplyed their wants, and contributed money to their reliefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Spaine.</head>
               <p>They write from <hi>Spaine,</hi> that howeuer the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in their fury haue proceeded in the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> yet haue the Inhabitants bin offered faire Conditions of Peace, &amp; remaining in quiet poſſeſſion of their eſtates ſo they will diſclaime the dependancy on any other States, &amp; acknowledge the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> their Lord and Protector: but whereas report hath ſent abroad diuers Thouſands of Duckets to pay the Soldiers, and diſcharge ſome Debts of importance and accompt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14994:11"/>the truth is, the ſiluer Fleet is not yet arriued, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſo watched by the Holanders in thoſe parts, that they cannot make that ſpeede as is deſired, ſo that there is as great complaining for want of money, as euer before, notwithſtanding the King not onely enlargeth his Court, but hath proceeded very nobly in diuers reformations, and ſet downe eſpeciall ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances for the augmentation of his owne honour, and detention of the Subiect in modeſt rules of duty and obſeruation, ſo that neither can euery man come to the Court as they were wont, nor thoſe that come, paſſe to ſuch places, as they accuſtomed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Fraunce.</head>
               <p>It hath pleaſed God ſo to diuert the King from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the warre againſt his Subiects, that heere is euery where a cheerefull face of concord and amity, and we doe not heare of any man that hath oppoſed againſt the meſſage of the Swiſs and Grizons, but that the King is willing to admit of their imploration for the defence, or if you will regayning the <hi>Valtoline,</hi> for which purpoſe there hath beene reciprocall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies betweene the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> and him, as farre as ſending of Preſents, and reſolution to continue a peace: but they neuer met in perſon, onely the Prince of <hi>Piemont</hi> and his wife haue beene at <hi>Lions,</hi> and great ioy is made on all ſides for the hopes men haue to thriue in their expectation, eſpecially conſidering the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rheimes</hi> propoſeth nothing, but obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Church, and an Vnity in Religion, diſclaiming the Ieſuites, intermedling with State matters, and peſtilentiall deuiſes, to ſet all in an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore againe: there hath paſſed diuers courteſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14994:12"/>Duke <hi>Heſpernon,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Condy,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and others of that ſide: and the Dukes <hi>Rohan</hi> and <hi>Subiſs,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Bulloigne</hi> himſelfe: as for the muſtring of Souldiers, and great preparation of diuers Armies, there is no ſuch matter as yet, more then a coniecture, that if the King will vndertake the buſineſſe of the Grizons, it cannot be done without ſufficient forces, and worthy Commaunders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Palatinate.</head>
               <p>The waters haue come downe ſo faſt this Winter, that they haue remoued <hi>Tilly</hi> from <hi>Frankendale,</hi> where that worthy Sergeant Maior <hi>Borregh</hi> hath not onely defended the place, but made many ſallyes to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damaging the Enemy, and ſupplying his own wants: but as I beleeue, neither <hi>Bauaria</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or he hath a purpoſe to continue there. For they neither fortifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, nor repaire the decayed places, or broken ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts, but rather demoliſh ſuch holds as may be made inexpugnable, eſpecially the Caſtle at <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> and the new Sconce at <hi>Mainhem,</hi> with other places which Captaine <hi>Dexter</hi> had beſtowed great paines about. The Duke of <hi>Bauarta</hi> himſelfe is gone to his owne Country to meete the Emperour and Empreſſe, who appointed to come thether, &amp; giue the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg</hi> audience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Cullen.</head>
               <p>The daily forraging of the Country by the Enemy on both ſides, hath raiſed diuers hurliburlies i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cullen,</hi> ſo that the Biſhop hath quite abandoned the Towne, and the whole lands of <hi>Weſtphalia Waſt, Luke,</hi> and <hi>Mank,</hi> lye expoſed to the fury of the Souldiers, who ſpate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14994:12"/>not to ſpoile both friends and foes, and although <hi>Gonzales</hi> with <hi>Graue Vanderberghen</hi> haue pretended to follow <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> and driue him out of <hi>Freeſland,</hi> for which purpoſe they came as farre as <hi>Lingen;</hi> yet they haue ſmally preuailed more then common intercepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as the troopes haue taken aduantage of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers weakeneſſe lying in Gariſon: yet they ſay, that <hi>Gonzales</hi> hath ſurpriſed the Towne of <hi>Roſſendorpe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Hauns</hi> Townes: As for <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> hee remaineth like a rocke vnmooueable, 12000. ſtrong, well armed, and as it ſhould ſeeme reſolued to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any action or attempt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From Amſterdam.</head>
               <p>Here is great preparation of ſhipping both for the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> and as great ioy for the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene the States and Eaſt <hi>India</hi> Company <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>London.</hi> They feaſt one another, and haue met i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Churches with publicke prayers and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: yea, the report of the buſineſſe at <hi>Ormus</hi> in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> is here ſo frequent, and well entertained, as if they had beene ſharers in the glory of the Engliſh: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they imagine the Portingals will prouide for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery in ſome ſtronger and ſufficient manner, they likewiſe prouide by way of preuention, extraordinary ſhips, prouiſion, and Mariners for the ſame place and purpoſe, and ſo determine to ioyne with the Engliſh in thoſe parts, if neede be: ſo that here is a iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on publiſhed, that they neither looked on in their dangerous fights, as Neuters, nor will hereafter giue way vnto any wrong or indignity, which ſhall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14994:13"/>
               <head>From Antwerpe.</head>
               <p>The comming downe of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> and <hi>Graue Henry</hi> to <hi>Breda,</hi> and ſo to ouer-looke <hi>Bergen</hi> with all her fortifications, which were preſently to be repaired, raiſed a fearefull hurli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burly in <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> as if the Towne were already beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or ſome Treaſon diſcouered amongſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, which feare of theirs was much augmented by the many Ships in a readineſſe at the mouth of the <hi>Scheld,</hi> where the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> loſt ſome of them, and diuers horſes by an vnlookt for Froſt, and ſo the breaking of the Ice vpon a ſuddaine: whereupon <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola</hi> and his Captaines taking ſome aduantage vnder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tence of making all ſure, would haue put in extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inary troopes of Horſe, and Companies of Foot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Towne: but the Inhabitants anſwered, They and a Caſtle or Citadell already, mand to commaund <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: what neede then any more for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Spin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>la</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot yet ſatisfied, vrged the neceſſity of manning their Ports in this ſuſpicious time, and therefore onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired admittance of foure Companies to keepe their Courts of Guard about the Ports with the Burgers: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was alſo denied, till at laſt vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etter deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration they admitted 4. Companies into the Town, but not to guard the Ports; who were no ſooner pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but <hi>Spinola</hi> conferres with the Commander of the Citadell, and ſo demaunds a lone of 120000. pound ſterling in ſo gentle a manner, as they knew not what to ſay, but that they were not able to disburſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
